<p id="PC_118d" class="noindent">
<b>8. <i>Summary of the argument up to this point.</i></b>
What we have seen so far can be summarized under four headings. The
culmination of this summary comes in 8.4.<br/>
<br/>
<b>8.1</b> The prior opening up of a world of praxis entails the understanding of<br/>
• means-to-ends relationships, which entails “a suitable means” and “the end to which it is suitable”;<br/>
• the job that the tool is suitable for doing;<br/>
• the final purpose of the whole chain of referrals.<br/>
<br/>
<b>8.2</b> Question: What am I “in” when I understand myself pre-theoretically as “in” a world of meaning?<br/>
<br/>
Answer: In understanding a set of practical relations, I understand myself, either tacitly or explicitly,<br/>
• as <i>able</i> to, and <i>having</i> to, become myself, whether I do that authentically or inauthentically<br/>
• as thrown into a purpose-oriented world of useful things, i.e., a world structured by the suitability of means
for achieving ends.<br/>
<br/>
<b>8.3</b> As ex-sisting,<br/>
• I am always directed “ahead” to some purpose or other.<br/>
• In terms of that purpose, I am referred “back” to a task.<br/>
• That task in turn refers me “further back” to the kind of tool that will be suitable for doing the job and
achieving the final purpose.<br/>
• In other words, insofar as I ex-sist, I let things be encountered as useful to my current final purpose. All the
referrals function for the sake of that final purpose.<br/>
<br/>
<b>8.4</b> Defining the essential structure of any and all worlds of praxis:<br/>
• I am always already in and referred to a set of means-to-ends relations.<br/>
• The things I encounter are likewise found within a set of means-to-ends relations.<br/>
• In a given world of praxis, both I and those things are directed to the same end.<br/>
• Both (1) my current final purpose and (2) the end to which these useful things are currently directed coincide,
and this togetherness constitutes a specific world of praxis.<br/>
• That togetherness, taken as the formal structure of all such worlds, is what we mean by the “worldhood” or
essence of any world of praxis.
</p>
