<p id="PC_114d" class="noindent">
<b>2. <i>The suitability of a means to an end.</i></b>
How does the world of praxis “free up” the being of tools? And why it is that
the first thing we meet is the useful? This and the next six paragraphs develop these questions in order to find the
essential structure of worlds of praxis.
</p>
<p id="PC_114d">
<b>2.1</b> The being of a tool is “to do a job with,” i.e., its being is the <i>referral</i> of the tool to doing something. Such
referrals can take various forms: serviceable-for, useful-for, or even damaged-and-currently-unusable.
</p>
<p id="PC_114d">
<b>2.2</b> The job the tool can do—what the hammer is useful <i>for</i>, or what the sign <i>indicates</i>—specifies the kind of
referral that a hammer or a sign has.
</p>
<p id="PC_114d">
<b>2.3</b> But a tool’s status as “for-doing-a-job” is an ontological factor—it defines what this thing is—not an ontic
property built into, say, a hammer or a sign. A tool’s properties, such as size or weight, can make that tool <i>appropriate</i>
for a task, but such properties remain ontic and do not constitute the being of the tool. (These ontic factors are “bound
up” with tools, not unlike the way objective presence is insofar as it can show up when a tool is damaged, missing, or
in the way.)
</p>
<p id="PC_114d">
<b>2.4</b> A tool’s <i>serviceability</i>, the fact that it is for-doing-a-job, is an ontological matter, and it is not the same as the
tool’s ontic appropriateness for a task. Serviceability is how this tool currently is; it is the tool’s current <i>being</i>. That
prior ontological status is the reason why I can find a tool to be ontically appropriate for the job.
</p>
<p id="PC_114d">
<b>2.5</b> What, then, do we mean in saying that the being of a tool is its <i>being referred</i> to doing some job? The actual
use of any tool is grounded in the tool’s prior ontological status of “is-for-doing-a-job.” This factor is operative <i>before</i>
I decide on what tool to use; in fact, it is what lets me <i>discover</i> something as useful for doing the job.
</p>
<p id="PC_114d">
<b>2.6</b> I use a tool as a means to an end when I see (or think I see) its suitability for doing the job. Such suitability
encompasses the suitability <i>of something</i> (the tool) <i>for something</i> (the job). <i>Suitability-of-and-for</i> constitutes the
referral-structure of a tool. It is what we mean when we say a tool’s being is the tool’s “being referred.”
</p>