<p id="PC_121e" class="noindent">
<b>15. <i>The response.</i></b> Our analysis has kept three things distinct:
</p>
<p id="PC_121e">
1. usefulness: the being of the things that we <i>initially</i> meet;
</p>
<p id="PC_121e">
2. objective presence: the being of things as encountered and determined by going through the useful things
that we initially meet;
</p>
<p id="PC_121e">
3. ex-sistence
</p>
<p id="PC_121e">
• as human being: we are the ontic condition that lets things be discovered as meaningful;
</p>
<p id="PC_121e">
• as the “worldhood” or essence of the world of meaning.<sup>¶</sup>
</p>
<p id="PC_121e" class="noindent">
The first two are categorial, i.e., they pertain to things that do not have ex-sistence. The third is an ex-sistential that
determines our nature as engagement with meaning.
</p>
<p id="PC_121e">
We <i>could</i> choose to understand the referrals that constitute meaningfulness-as-such as merely “a system of
relations,” but such a formalization flattens out these referrals and misses their real experiential content. These
supposedly “simple” relations (means-to-end, in-order-to, and the like) and their relata are in fact what constitute
meaningfulness. Their experienced content resists mathematical functionalization. Nor are they not just “ideas”
posited in “mere thinking.” Rather, these relations are where practical foresight actually lives and sustains itself.
</p>
<p id="PC_121e">
We do not “volatize” the “substantial being” of the useful. On the contrary we provide the basis for understanding
these things substantively, that is, in themselves. Only because things can be encountered as useful can they also be
encountered as “just out there” in the form of “substances.” If taken as just objectively present, these relations <i>might</i>
have their “properties” mathematically determined in “functional concepts.” But such concepts apply ontologically
<i>only</i> to things whose being is taken as “substantiality.” Such functional concepts are formalized concepts that apply
always and only to “substances.”
</p>