<p id="PC_23b" class="noindent">
<b>5. <i>Second: “As the most universal, being is indefinable”—but it still remains a problem.</i></b> This indefinability
is deduced from the fact that being is the most universal.<sup>4</sup> As far as it goes, that is true insofar as “definitio
fit per genus proximum et differentiam specificam”
<span style="color:magenta;" title="This maxim regarding genus and specific difference 
(γένος and ἐιδοποιός διαφορά) derives from Aristotle, Posterior Analytics II 13 and Topics
V-VI (see also Locke, An Essay Concerning Human Understanding, chap. 3, n. 10).
For example, we define “human being” by locating it under/within the genus “animal” and, within
that genus, under the species “rational animal.”">◊</span> [Things are defined in terms of their closest genus and
their specific difference.] But this means we cannot definte being, insofar as<br />
• being is not a thing: “enti non additur aliqua natura.”
<span style="color:magenta;" title="A free citation of Thomas Aquinas, De veritate, I, 1, responsio
(which actually reads “Sed enti non possunt addi aliqua”). 
Here “ens” (dative “enti”) refers not to a thing that has being
but rather to the very having-of-being.">◊</span> “Being” cannot be determined by having
anything entitative added to it.<br />
• and secondly, insofar as being is the highest, most general concept, it cannot be placed under a
genus—i.e., it cannot be derived from or defined in terms of anything higher. (Likewise it cannot
be represented by anything <i>lower</i> than itself).<br />
Nonetheless, the “is” of things—their way of being—is still a problem to be solved. We are simply saying
that being cannot be a <i>thing</i>.
<span style="color:magenta;" title="No! Rather, it’s that nothing can be decided about the
clearing [<i>Seyn</i>] with the help of such conceptuality.">☞</span> 
Therefore, it can’t be defined by way of a logic that is based on a traditional
ontology and that applies only to things rather than to the “is” or <i>way of being</i> of things. So even though we
cannot define being, we still have to ask: What accounts for the fact that we can and do understand it?
<br/>
<sup>4</sup> Pascal, Pensées et Opuscules, 6th revised edition, ed. Léon Brunschvicg (Paris: Librairie Hachette, 1912),
169.12-16: “One cannot undertake to define ‘being’ without falling into this absurdity: one cannot define a
word without beginning with this: ‘It is…,’ either expressed or implied. Therefore, to define ‘being’ one
has to say ‘It is…,’ thereby using the very word that is defined [in the definition].” The text is from the
Opuscules, “De l’Esprit géométrique et de l’Art de persuader” [ca. 1658], section 1.
</p>