<p id="PC_34d" class="noindent">
<b>11. <i>Traditional philosophy glimpsed the ontic-ontological priority of human being.</i></b> Early on,
philosophers did see the ontic-ontological priority of ex-sistence but did not grasp or problematize it. For
example:<br />
  • Parmenides [frag. 3: νοεῖν and εἶναι “go together.”]
  <span style="color:magenta;" title="Diehls@ sp@ : τὸ γὰρ αὐτὸ νοεῖν ἐστίν τε καὶ εἶναι.
I translate noein (νοεῖν) as “to mind” in the specific sense of “to have something directly and immediately
present to mind; to intuit intellectually.” Heidegger interprets τὸ αὐτό in terms of “go together,” “are
correlative,” rather than “are the same.”">◊</span><br />
  • Aristotle: ἡ ψυχὴ τὰ ὄντα πώς ἐστι πάντα.<sup>1</sup> “Man’s
being is somehow all things.”
<span style="color:magenta;" title="De anima III 8, 431b21: Heidegger writes: ἡ ψυχὴ τὰ ὄντα πώς ἐστι 
(“The psychē is somehow things”), mistakenly omitting the word πάντα (panta), “all.” 
On the twenty-fifth anniversary of the publication of SZ he corrected it: 
“Das πάντα ist in S.u.Z. aus Versehen herausgeblieben”
(“In SZ the πάντα was left out by mistake”):
lecture course “Übungen im Lesen,” February 13, 1952, omitted at GA 83: 654.8.">◊</span>
That is, ψυχή (man’s being) has αἴσθησις (sensation), which
discovers data, and νόησις (mind), which discovers the <i>being</i> of things: what and that they <i>are</i>.<br />
  • Thomas Aquinas: In his work the ontic-ontological priority of human being over things emerges
but is not clarified. He worked out the “transcendentals” (<i>transcendentia</i>), i.e., the most basic,
trans-generic characteristics of things, characteristics that lie beyond any <i>modus specialis entis</i> [=
beyond all species and genera of things]. One of those transcendental characteristics is <i>verum</i> [the
intrinsic openness of things to the understanding]. He demonstrated this via the nature of the soul,
which is ens quod natum est convenire cum omni ente, i.e., a thing that by its very nature “comes
together with”
<span style="color:magenta;" title="GA 2: 19.16 adds the phrase “d.h. übereinzukommen,” i.e., “that is, agrees with.”">◊</span>
 all other things, but Aquinas did not clarify this.<sup>2</sup><br />
Obviously, all of this has nothing to do with “subjectivizing” everything.
<br/>
<br/>
<sup>1</sup> De anima III 8, 431b21; cf. III 5, 430a14ff. [See Editor’s note.]<br />
<sup>2</sup> Thomas Aquinas, <i>Quaestiones de veritate</i> qu. I a. 1 corpus. Cf. the short work “De natura generis,” a
somewhat more robust “deduction” of the transcendentals that deviates from the <i>De veritate</i>.
<span style="color:magenta;" title="That work is of dubious authenticity.
It is online at http://www.documentacatholicaomnia.eu/03d/1225-274,_Thomas_Aquinas,_De_Natura_Generis,_LT.pdf.">◊</span>
</p>