<p id="PC_41b">
<b>“Alreadiness” and the past.</b> Factically I always am “what” and how I <i>already</i> am [“wie und ‘was’ es schon war”].<sup>¶</sup>
This entails that, whether I am aware of it or not, I always already am my <i>past</i>—but not like some possession that I drag
along behind me that still occasionally affects me. No, I <i>am</i> my past: it is an element of my way of being. Moreover, (to
put it roughly) my past “happens” from out of my future.<sup>¶</sup>
</p>
<p id="PC_41b">
Regardless of how I now am and currently understand my ex-sistence, I have grown up <i>into</i> and <i>in</i> an <i>inherited</i>
way of understanding myself. That is how I first and foremost understand myself, it’s how I see and regulate my
possibilities. My inherited past—which is always <i>social</i>, i.e., the past of my “generation” (Dilthey)—does not follow
along <i>behind</i> me but always already goes <i>ahead</i> of me.<sup>¶</sup>
</p>
<p id="PC_41b">
¶ <b>1, alreadiness</b>: We are always our “essence,” or as Heidegger puts it (channeling Aristotle’s τὸ τί ἦν εἶναι): our
“wie und ‘was’ es schon war.” Cf. GA 2: 114, note a, which is reproduced in our note to “a priori perfect” at SZ 85b.
¶ 1, <b><i>my past</i>. . . drag along behind me</b>: This phrase (“‘hinter’ ihm herschiebt,” SZ 20.7) recalls another from
Heidegger’s review of Jasper’s <i>Psychologie der Weltanschauungen</i>, GA 9: 3.32 = 27.25: “eine mitgeschleppte
Beigabe.”<br />
¶ 1, <b>my past “happens” from out of my future</b>: The past is not the same as “alreadiness” (one’s essence as das
Gewesene). Whereas one’s past “happens” from out of one’s futurity, one’s futurity is based in and generated from
out of one’s alreadiness: SZ 344b: “aus ihr [= Gewesenheit] erst Zukunft und Gegenwart sich zeitigen.”<br />
¶ 1, <b>already goes ahead of me</b>: Alreadingess (das Gewesene) always goes ahead of ex-sistence (“west ihr stets
voraus”: GA 11: 58.3). Likewise thrownness does not lie “behind” ex-sistence (“liegt nicht hinter ihm,” SZ 284b). Re
generation: see SZ 384c, below, and Hans Ulrich Lessing, Rudolf A. Makkreel, and Riccardo Pozzo, editors.
<i>Recent Contributions to Dilthey’s Philosophy of the Human Sciences</i>. Stuttgart: Fromann-Holzboog, 2011, 26-31.
</p>