<p id="PC_51b" class="noindent">
<b>6. <i>The primary and secondary senses of phenomenon.</i></b> In its <i>primary</i> sense, ϕαινόμενον (from middle voice ϕαίνεσθαι,
to show up) is “that-which-shows-up”: something insofar as it is open and manifest to us. The verb ϕαίνω means to
bring something to the light of day, to place it in the light. Its stem ϕα- is related to ϕῶς, “light” in the sense of
brightness: that <i>wherein</i> something becomes manifest or visible.
</p>
<p id="PC_51b">
In its <i>primary</i> sense a ϕαινόμενον is what shows up in and of itself, what is manifest. In the plural, φαινόμενα are
all things that lie in the light of day, i.e., what the Greeks sometimes called τὰ ὄντα (things). A thing can show up in and
of itself in many ways, depending on our access to it.
</p>
<p id="PC_51b">
In a <i>secondary</i> sense ϕαινόμενον can mean “mere semblance” when something shows up as it is <i>not</i> so that it
merely “looks like” or “seems to be.” (In Aristotle, φαινόμενον ἀγαθόν means the <i>mere semblance</i> of the good:
<i>Eudemian Ethics</i>, VII 2, 1235b25.)
</p>
<p id="PC_51b">
The connection between the primary and the secondary meanings of ϕαινόμενον is this: Only because something
claims to show up as a true phenomenon can it show up as a mere semblance. That is, the primary sense is already
included in the secondary sense, and the secondary sense is a privative modification of the primary one. We reserve the
term φαινόμενον for the primary sense.
</p>
<p id="PC_51b">
As regards what immediately follows: A “phenomenon” is an appearance, but there are two meanings of
appearance that we exclude from the field of <i>proper</i> phenomena, namely (1) “appearance by way of something else”
and (2) “mere appearance” à la Kant. We take up each in turn.
</p>
<p id="PC_51b" style="text-align:center;">
PHENOMENA
</p>
<p id="PC_51b">
<b>Primary sense</b>
</p>
<p id="PC_51b">
1. A genuine phenomenon: something that shows up as it is
</p>
<p id="PC_51b">
<b>Secondary sense</b>
</p>
<p id="PC_51b">
2. A semblance: something merely seems to show up, or shows up as it is not
</p>
<p id="PC_51b">
<b>Two excluded senses: two forms of “appearance” [<i>Erscheinung</i>]</b>
</p>
<p id="PC_51b">
3. “Appearances” through which another hidden thing shows up indirectly (e.g., symptoms, symbols)
</p>
<p id="PC_51b">
4. “Mere appearances” (Kant)
</p>