<p id="PC_57b" class="noindent">
<b>20. <i>Function-5: making a judgment.</i></b> By considering the original meaning of the noun <i>alētheia</i>
and the verb <i>alētheuein</i>, we can see that it is a gross misunderstanding to invoke Aristotle as the
source of the erroneous thesis that the primary locus of alētheia—the primary place where sense
is made of something—is the judgment underlying a declarative statement.
<!--
<span style="color:magenta;" title="On Heidegger’s important distinctions regarding the kinds and levels of alētheia,
see the editorial note to § 44 ¶ 5, “the original experience of alētheia among the Greeks.”">◊</span>
-->
<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp; Judgment as an act of synthesis is not the primary locus of <i>alētheia</i> as disclosure. On the
contrary, in comparison with <i>logos</i> as the <i>synthetic</i> apprehension of what something is and how it
operates, Aristotle holds to two forms of <i>non</i>-synthetic apprehension that are more fundamental.
<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp; 1. Sense perception (<i>aisthēsis</i>) discloses things more originally than does <i>logos</i>-qua-judgment,
insofar as
<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; • Every sense faculty aims directly and exclusively at its proper object (its <i>idiom</i>,
plural <i>idia</i>).
<button id="Btn57b1" style="color:magenta;">◊</button>
<dialog id="Dlg57b1">
    <p style="text-indent:2em;">
        Commenting on <i>De anima</i> II 6, 418al1 and <i>De anima</i> III 3, 427b12, Heidegger says: “An
<i>idion</i> is something accessible through one specific manner of perceiving and only through that manner of perceiving. 
It has the character of being <i>aei alēthes</i>, i.e., always disclosive of its object.
<a href="https://www.beyng.com/gaselis/?vol=17&amp;pg=8">GA 17: 8</a>.15-17 = 5.24-26.
    </p>
    <form style="float:right;" method="dialog">
        <button>Close</button>
    </form>
</dialog>
The proper object of the eye is color, that of the ear is sound (the
eye does not hear sound, and the ear does not see color), and so on.
<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; • Moreover, that proper object of sense perception is immediately disclosed
through the correlative organ <i>without needing a mediating synthesis</i> to bring
together the sense faculty and its proper object.
<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; • Therefore, sense perception, as non-synthetic, is always disclosive (<i>alēthes</i>) of
its objects and can never be mistaken (pseudes). I either see color, or I don't see
at all.
<button id="Btn57b2" style="color:magenta;">◊</button>
<dialog id="Dlg57b2">
    <p style="text-indent:2em;">
        Cf. Stephen Dedalus' musings on Aristotle and sight,
“Ineluctable modality of the visible”: James Joyce, <i>Ulysses</i> (Gabler ed.), 31.1.
    </p>
    <form style="float:right;" method="dialog">
        <button>Close</button>
    </form>
</dialog>
<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp; 2. Pure intellectual intuition (<i>noein/noēsis</i>) has its object directly and immediately
present-to-mind. It is the non-synthetic apprehension not of a <i>thing</i> but of the simplest
elements of what and how the thing <i>is</i>: the thing's <i>being</i>. As direct and non-synthetic,
intellectual intuition is likewise always <i>alēthes</i>/disclosive in the purest and most
original sense. It can never “cover something over,” it can never be incorrect. Either I
have the being of something present-to-mind (<i>noein</i>) 
or I do not know it at all (<i>agnoein</i>).
<button id="Btn57b3" style="color:magenta;">◊</button>
<dialog id="Dlg57b3">
    <p style="text-indent:2em;">
        <i>Metaphysics</i> IX 10, 1052a2. Cf. <a href="https://www.beyng.com/gaselis/?vol=21&amp;pg=177">GA 21: 177</a>.10-20 = 
        <a href="https://www.beyng.com/pages/en/Logic/Logic.158.html">158</a>.13-159.10.
    </p>
    <form style="float:right;" method="dialog">
        <button>Close</button>
    </form>
</dialog>
</p>