<p id="PC_56c" class="noindent">
<b>17. <i>Function-2: showing something in speech.</i></b> In its fully concretized form, enacting a <i>logos</i> is a
matter of displaying something in <i>phonē</i>, vocalized sound, 
indeed in <i>phōnē meta phantasias</i>,
<button id="Btn56c1" style="color:magenta;">◊</button>
<dialog id="Dlg56c1">
    <p style="text-indent:2em;">
        Heidegger unites <i>phōnē</i> from <i>De anima</i> II 8, 420b 29 with <i>meta phantasias</i>
         from ibid., 420b 32. The word <i>phantasia</i> comes from <i>phantazō</i>: to make something
visible. Heidegger interprets <i>phantasia</i> as the ability of an animated (<i>empsychos</i>) entity to <i>show</i>
something, i.e., to make it understandable and understood. (Cf. “Φαντασία—daß sich etwas zeigt,”
<a href="https://www.beyng.com/gaselis/?vol=17&amp;pg=15">GA 17: 15</a>.18 = 11.5f.; Aristotle distinguishes between</p>
<p style="margin-left:2em;">1. <i>psophos</i> (Latin, sonus): either
</p>
<p style="margin-left:4em;">1.1 the noise made by two solid objects hitting each other in the medium of air or
water (<i>De anima</i> II 8, 419b 4-25, 420a 3-420b 6); or
</p>
<p style="margin-left:4em;">1.2 the inarticulate sound of an animal (<i>agrammatos psophos</i>, cf. <i>Peri hermeneias</i> 16a 29).
</p>
<p style="margin-left:2em;">2. <i>phōnē</i> (Latin, vox): a vocalization, i.e., an articulate sound uttered by a human being as a
means to living well, <i>to eu</i> (<i>De anima</i> II 8, 420b 5—421a 6; <i>phōnē</i> here is synonymous with
<i>dialektos</i> and <i>hermēneia</i> in its secondary sense (ibid. 420b 18-20; cf. Editorial note to ¶ 35,
“<i>hermeneutical</i>,” below). Producing <i>phōnē</i> requires not only
</p>
<p style="margin-left:4em;">2.1 respiration (<i>anapnoē</i>: ibid., 420b 15f., 26f.) and
</p>
<p style="margin-left:4em;">2.2 throat, windpipe, lungs (<i>pharungx?? artēria, pleumōn</i>: ibid. 420b 23f., 29)
but also and above all
</p>
<p style="margin-left:4em;">2.3 <i>phantasia</i> the ability to bring things to understanding, which goes with
</p>
<p style="margin-left:4em;">2.4 the ability to <i>sēmainein</i>, to indicate matters to others.
Thus Aristotle defines a <i>phōnē</i> as a sound made by a living entity that brings something to
a meaningful understanding (ibid., II 8, 420b 29-32).
    </p>
    <form style="float:right;" method="dialog">
        <button>Close</button>
    </form>
</dialog>
vocalized sound that makes something manifest in its meaning and thus understandable. In
speaking with another person, I let him or her “see” (i.e., understand) what I'm talking about,
regardless of whether I am right or wrong, honest or dishonest.
</p>