<p id="PC_56e" class="noindent">
<b>19. <i>Function-4: making sense of something as this or that.</i></b> We said that <i>logos</i> as <i>synthesis</i> makes
sense of a thing <i>as</i> this or that, i.e., in terms of a certain meaning; thus, a <i>logos</i> can be what the
Greeks called “disclosive” (<i>alēthes</i>). Here we have to make an important distinction.
<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp; In other contexts, the adjective <i>alēthes</i> and the noun <i>alētheia</i> can have the <i>derivative</i>
meanings of, respectively, “true/correct” and “truth/correctness,” referring to the so-called
“agreement” between a thing (S) and what is predicated about it (P). However, in the present
context, the adjective ἀ <i>alēthes</i> does not have the derivative meaning of “true” vs. “false.” Rather,
it has the <i>original</i> sense of the verb <i>alētheuein</i>:
<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp; • <i>a-</i>: the alpha privative, indicating the negation of what follows;
<button id="Btn56e1" style="color:magenta;">◊</button>
<dialog id="Dlg56e1">
    <p style="text-indent:2em;">
    <i>to alpha sterētikon</i> or ā: cf. <i>Metaphysics</i> V 22, 1022b32.
    </p>
    <form style="float:right;" method="dialog">
        <button>Close</button>
    </form>
</dialog>
<!--
<span style="color:magenta;" title="to alpha sterētikon or ā: cf. Metaphysics V 22, 1022b32.">◊</span>
-->
&nbsp;&nbsp; • <i>lēthē</i>: “hiddenness, closed-off-ness.”
<br/>
The noun <i>alēthes</i> and the verb <i>alētheuō</i> originally refer to taking something out of “hiddenness,”
i.e., a state of not-being-understood, and bringing that thing into a state of being-understood 
(<i>a-lēth-eia</i>), regardless of whether the understanding is correct or not.
<button id="Btn56e2" style="color:magenta;">◊</button>
<dialog id="Dlg56e2">
    <p style="text-indent:2em;">
        The result is simply meaningfulness, <i>alētheia</i>-2, whether that
meaning be true/correct (cf. <i>alētheia</i>-3) or false/incorrect (<i>pseudos</i>). See <i>Physics</i> III 1, 200b 13-15
where Aristotle equates <i>lanthanein</i>: to lie hidden) and <i>agnoeisthai</i>: to not know). Cf. also
Heraclitus, fragment 1: those without <i>logos</i> forget (<i>epilanthanontai</i>), i.e.: what they do remains
hidden (<i>lanthanei</i>).
    </p>
    <form style="float:right;" method="dialog">
        <button>Close</button>
    </form>
</dialog>
<!--
<span style="color:magenta;" title="The result is simply meaningfulness, alētheia-2, whether that
meaning be true/correct (cf. alētheia-3) or false/incorrect (pseudos). See Physics III 1, 200b 13-15
where Aristotle equates lanthanein: to lie hidden) and agnoeisthai: to not know). Cf. also
Heraclitus, fragment 1: those without logos forget (epilanthanontai), i.e.: what they do remains
hidden (lanthanei).">◊</span>
-->
<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp; To enact a <i>logos</i> (verb form, <i>legein</i>) is to perform an act of <i>a-lēth-euein</i>, i.e., to dis-close
something, to make sense of it. One way of disclosing a thing is by way of <i>apophainesthai</i>, making
sense of it by drawing that sense from the thing itself rather than from one's wishes or feelings
regarding the thing. The act of <i>legein</i> is the same as the act of <i>alētheuein</i> in the form of <i>apophainesthai</i>:
understanding the thing <i>as</i> this or that (understanding Socrates <i>as</i> a threat to Athens).
But again: to dis-close or make sense of something (<i>a-lēth-euein</i>) is simply to understand it, not
necessarily to understand it correctly.
<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp; Hence, the third of function of <i>logos</i>—synthesizing a thing with a possible meaning—is
the same as this fourth function, <i>a-lēth-euein</i> disclosing, making sense of something as this or that.
In this original and primary sense, the corresponding adjective <i>alēthes</i> means: not-hidden, uncovered,
dis-covered, dis-closed—in a word: understood. In the act of <i>legein</i> as <i>alētheuein</i>, I
metaphorically take the object out of its hiddenness (its not-understood-ness) by making sense of
it as having this or that meaning.
<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp; The opposite of <i>alētheuein</i> is <i>pseudesthai</i>, “to be false or incorrect.” That word means “to
lie or deceive”—metaphorically, to cover something up and close it off from understanding: to
mislead someone (even myself) by declaring the thing to be what it is not.
</p>