<p id="PC_56b" class="noindent">
<b>16. <i>Function-1: showing something in its meaning, whether correctly or not.</i></b><span style="color:magenta;" title="">◊</span> 
A <i>logos</i> Aristotle
says, has the basic function of <i>dēloun</i>, making manifest what one is talking about. A <i>logos</i> makes
sense of a thing by displaying that thing (the subject of the sentence) in terms of a <i>specific</i> meaning
(represented by the predicate). Aristotle specifies the function of <i>dēloun</i> more precisely as <i>apophainesthai</i>
to display something (<i>-phainesthai</i>) in predicative terms that are drawn <i>from (apo-)
the thing itself</i>.<sup>1</sup> We can better understand <i>apophainesthai</i> by separating out its two component
parts, namely (1) “to display/make manifest,” and (2) “from.”<br />
 • <i>--phainesthai</i>: When I perform an act of <i>logos</i>, I purport to manifest to myself or my
interlocutor how and as what something actually is.
<br />
• <i>apo-</i>: Moreover, I draw the sense that I make of the thing <i>from the thing itself</i> rather
than from my feelings, desires, or hopes about the thing.<span style="color:magenta;" title="In
a de-clarative sentence (apo-phansis, de-claratio) I clarify the subject matter in predicative terms
that are taken from (apo-, de-) the subject matter itself rather than from how I feel (etc.) about the
subject matter. See the second Editorial note to ¶ 6, “Such things can appear as they are in many
ways, depending on how we have access to them,” above.">◊</span>
<br/>
An apophantic sentence (an assertion or proposition) makes the claim that what I am saying is an
unqualified fact. Such a sentence is in the indicative/declarative mood. In Greek it is called an
<i>apophansis</i>: it claims to show something (<i>-phansis</i>) as having a meaning that I draw <i>from (apo-)
the thing itself</i> rather than from my subjective attitudes about the thing. Declarative statements are
meaningful (i.e., understandable) regardless of whether the meaning is correct or not.<span style="color:magenta;" title="At § 44 ¶ 23
(SZ 220.7ff. = 262.36ff.) Heidegger will characterize this paragraph as a “dogmatic” presentation of
logos and alētheia as contrasted with the phenomenological demonstration he provides in § 44.">◊</span> For
<br/>
However, not every meaningful sentence is in the indicative/declarative mood.<span style="color:magenta;" title="Aristotle
holds that every articulate utterance is meaningful/understandable: it can bring something present to
mind; however, not every articulate utterance shows something and claims that what it shows is a
fact. (De interpretatione 17a 1-3: Every logos is meaningful/understandable, but not every logos
necessarily declarative.) Grammatical moods are ways that I can express how I and my sentence are
related to the meaningful/understandable thing. Ancient Greek grammar knew of five moods
(engkliseis; singular, engklisis): the indicative (hē horistikē the imperative (hē protatikē), the optative
(hē eutikē), the subjunctive (hē hypotaktikē), and paradoxically the indefinite/infinitive (hē
aparemphatos: cf. a + para + en + phainō: not-indicating-[a mood]).">◊</span> For
example, a request (<i>euchē</i>) such as “Please pass the salt” is understandable but neither true nor
false.
<br/>
<br/>
<sup>1</sup> <i>De interpretatione</i> 1-6; also <i>Metaphysics</i> VII 4 and <i>Nicomachean Ethics VI</i>
</p>