<p id="PC_53c" class="noindent">
<b>10. <i>Phenomena as “mere appearances” in Kant.</i></b> The possible confusion increases due to a fourth
meaning of “appearance,” namely “mere appearances” in the <i>Critique of Pure Reason</i>. To explain
this fourth meaning, we will use an analogy to understand what Kant is getting at.
<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp; Say I think of a symptom (e.g., a rash) as a genuine, self-showing phenomenon that
<i>emanates from</i> the disease. In turn, say I see that the disease will never be able to appear directly
and thus can never become a genuine phenomenon. In so doing, I see the rash
<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp; • as <i>brought forth</i> by the disease, i.e., emanating from it, and
<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp; • as <i>pointing to</i> the disease insofar as the disease manifests itself indirectly through
the rash. In this sense the rash is a “mere appearance” of the disease that remains
hidden “behind” the rash.
<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp; • Note, however, that as mentioned at the end of ¶ 7, we do not call the rash a “mere
semblance”—an appearance-2—inasmuch as it does not hide or obscure a genuine
phenomenon.
<br />
Kant uses the word “appearance” (Erscheinung) in a twofold sense that is analogous to this
example.
<br />
&nbsp;&nbsp; • On the one hand, in Kant empirical appearances <i>do show themselves</i> as the objects of
empirical intuition. In that regard, they are genuine phenomena in our sense of the term.
<span style="color:magenta;" title="But Heidegger's
sense of “phenomenon” is not the same as Kant's. In the “Aesthetic” Kant defined appearance as:
“the undetermined object of an empirical intuition” (A 34/B 20). All objects of empirical intuition
are appearances, but phenomena only those appearances that are “thought in accordance with the
unity of the categories.” (A 248/B 305 Analogous (but only analogous) to Kant's distinction
between appearances (Erscheinungen) and phenomena might be Heidegger's distinction between
what appears and how it appears, i.e., between (1) das Seiende considered without explicit
reference to its Sein and (2) das Seiende considered in terms of its Sein.">◊</span>
<br />
&nbsp;&nbsp; • On the other hand, however, these empirical appearances are <i>emanations from</i> the
noumena, which remain hidden “behind” those empirical appearances.
<br />
The empirical appearances (phenomena as mere <i>Erscheinungen</i> in Kant) are “mere appearances”
in Kant's sense of that term: they do not bring the noumena to self-manifestation.
</p>