<p id="PC_51b" class="noindent">
<b>6. <i>Appearance-1: a genuine phenomenon.</i></b> 
In its primary sense, the Greek word <i>phainomenon</i>
means “a thing insofar as it appears to us.”
<button id="Btn51b1" style="color:magenta;">◊</button>
<dialog id="Dlg51b1">
    <p style="text-indent:2em;">
        (1) At <a href="https://www.beyng.com/gaselis/?vol=17&amp;pg=6">GA 17: 6</a>.11-13 = 4.3-5 Heidegger eschews the German word 
“Erscheinung” as a translation of <i>phainomenon</i> because,
as he rightly points out, “it creates confusion.” However, the English “appearance” is a good
rendering of <i>phainomenon</i>, especially since the “ap-” (Latin, ad) indicates that a phenomenon
always implies a dative, a “to whom” of the appearing.
</p>
<p style="text-indent:2em;">
    (2) Heidegger will give the briefest definition of the primary and deformalized (¶ 27) sense
of “phenomenon” at <a href="https://www.beyng.com/pages/de/SeinUndZeit/SeinUndZeit.097.html">SZ 97</a>.14f. = 
<a href="https://www.beyng.com/btapp/page/130">130</a>.8f. (§ 21, ¶ 6): “etwas an ihm selbst Erfahrenes und in
solcher Erfahrung Bestimmbares”; that is:
</p>
<p style="margin-left:4em;text-indent:-2em;">• a <i>what</i>: something that we experience (etwas…Erfahrenes)
</p>
<p style="margin-left:4em;text-indent:-2em;">• in <i>how</i> it shows up, i.e., in its way of being (an ihm selbst),
</p>
<p style="margin-left:4em;text-indent:-2em;">• such that we can determine both the <i>what</i> and the <i>how</i> of what we experience, i.e., (1)
the <i>thing</i> (2) in its <i>way of being</i> (in solcher Erfahrung Bestimmbares).
    </p>
    <form style="float:right;" method="dialog">
        <button>Close</button>
    </form>
</dialog>
The word <i>phainomenon</i> derives from the verb
<i>phainesthai</i>, the present aorist infinitive, middle voice, of <i>phainō</i>, “to bring to light.” The stem of
<i>phainō</i> is <i>pha</i>-, which is also the stem of <i>phōs</i>, “light, brightness,” i.e., the medium in which
something becomes visible.
<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp; The primary and genuine sense of <i>phainomenon</i> is “something that appears as itself” In the
plural, <i>phainomena</i> (plural) refers to all things insofar as they are in, or can be brought into, “the
light of day.” <i>Phainomena</i> are what the Greeks sometimes called <i>ta onta</i>, “whatever-is.” Such
things can appear as they are in many ways, depending on how we have access to them.
<button id="Btn51b2" style="color:magenta;">◊</button>
<dialog id="Dlg51b2">
    <p style="text-indent:2em;">
        In this paragraph (at respectively,
        <a href="https://www.beyng.com/pages/de/SeinUndZeit/SeinUndZeit.028.html">SZ 28</a>.33 and .37 = 
        <a href="https://www.beyng.com/btapp/page/51">51</a>.12 and 16) 
Heidegger uses two phrases to indicate <i>how</i> a genuine phenomenon shows up:
“in itself” (an ihm selbst) and “from itself” (von ihm selbst her).
</p>
<p style="text-indent:2em;">
    The “in itself” is fairly straightforward: it refers to something showing up <i>as it really is</i> in
contrast to showing up as <i>is not</i> “[wie es] an ihm selbst <i>nicht</i> ist” (SZ 28.38f. = 51.18). This is the
difference between a genuine and a specious appearance.
</p>
<p style="text-indent:2em;">
    However, the “from itself” is more complex. It too is about how something shows up; but
at issue now is my access to and attitude about what shows up. The phenomenological correlation
is operative here: my access to and attitude about what shows up is correlative to and co-determines
the mode of its appearance, i.e., how the thing appears to me. That correlation of access 
and mode-of-appearance can be expressed in terms of the <i>grammatical mood</i> of a sentence.
</p>
<p style="margin-left:4em;text-indent:-2em;">
    • A sentence in the indicative (aka “realis”) mood purports to show the subject matter,
without qualification, just as it is, independent of my feelings, wishes, hopes, demands,
etc. regarding the thing.
</p>
<p style="margin-left:4em;text-indent:-2em;">
    • My feelings, wishes, etc. about the issue can be expressed by way of “irrealis”
grammatical moods: the subjunctive, optative, imperative, and so on.
</p>
<p>
A thing shows up and is experienced correlative to who/what I am and thus how I appropriate it.
Cf. the scholastic axiom “Quidquid recipitur, recipitur secundum modum recipientis”: Whatever
is received is received according to the mode of the recipient” and “Cognitum autem est in
cognoscente secundum modum cognoscentis” (<i>Summa theologiae</i> I, 12, 4, corpus): The known is
in the knower according to the mode of the knower. If my intent is to see what the thing is 
<i>in and of itself</i> apart from my subjective feelings (etc.) about it—that is, if I approach it with an indicative-declarative
attitude—the thing will ideally be seen as it is in itself; or to speak
anthropomorphically, it will “show itself from itself.” However, we must note two things:
</p>
<p style="margin-left:4em;text-indent:-2em;">
    • I can approach a thing with an indicative-declarative attitude, but my best intentions
notwithstanding, I can still end up seeing the thing as it is not. In other words, accessing
something with an indicative-declarative attitude, or uttering a sentence in the realisindicative
mood, is to claim that I am seeing and showing the thing as in fact it is; but
it is no guarantee that what I see and say will be what is actually the case. I may
sincerely believe and say in the indicative/realis mood that Socrates was born in
Thebes, but I would be wrong. Or I could in fact be intentionally lying when I tell
someone that.
</p>
<p style="margin-left:4em;text-indent:-2em;">
    • The faux reflexive “sich zeigen” along with the anthropomorphic “from ‘itself,’” might
make one think that things <i>show themselves</i> (middle voice) as if they possessed some
sort of personal agency. But no, as distinct from persons, things just “show up” (rather
than “showing themselves”) correlative to the access and attitude that one brings to the
experience.
    </p>
    <form style="float:right;" method="dialog">
        <button>Close</button>
    </form>
</dialog>
<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp; <b><i>Appearance-2: a mere semblance.</i></b> Appearance-2, the secondary and non-genuine sense of
<i>phainomenon</i>, is a mere semblance or specious appearance, something that appears as what it is
not. It merely “looks like” or “seems to be” this or that. In Aristotle, for example, a <i>phainomenon</i>
agathon means “a mere semblance of the good.”
<button id="Btn51b3" style="color:magenta;">◊</button>
<dialog id="Dlg51b3">
    <p>
    <i>Eudemian Ethics</i>, VII 2, 1235b25
    </p>
    <form style="float:right;" method="dialog">
        <button>Close</button>
    </form>
</dialog>
<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp; The structural connection between the primary and the secondary meanings of
<i>phainomenon</i> is this: Only because a thing <i>can</i> appear to us as it is (i.e., can be a genuine
phenomenon) can it also appear <i>as what it is not</i>/ (= a specious appearance). In other words, the
secondary sense presumes the primary one, and the primary sense always underlies the secondary
one. To put it differently: 
the secondary sense is a “privative modification” of the primary one.
<button id="Btn51b4" style="color:magenta;">◊</button>
<dialog id="Dlg51b4">
    <p style="text-indent:2em;">
        Here, as frequently elsewhere, Heidegger adopts and adapts 
Aristotle's notion of <i>sterēsis</i>, “privation” or “deprivation” (<i>Metaphysics</i> V 22).
Privation is a <i>positive</i> factor in the being of a thing—that is, it helps to define
the thing as what is is—but it does so by showing that the thing lacks something. 
In the case of a <i>sterēsis</i>, the fact that a thing is not this or that 
(the thing's “Nichthaben”) co-constitutes the being of the thing.
As Heidegger puts it, the fact that something is <i>not</i> this or that is what constitutes that
thing's being (“daß es das und das nicht ist macht sein Sein aus”: 
<a href="https://www.beyng.com/gaselis/?vol=18&amp;pg=4">GA 18: 4</a>.4-7 = 3.5-4.2 and = 201-03.)
    </p>
    <form style="float:right;" method="dialog">
        <button>Close</button>
    </form>
</dialog>
By just <i>looking like</i> a genuine appearance, a mere semblance “deprives” a genuine appearance of
its genuineness.
<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp; We will reserve the term “phenomenon” for the first and genuine sense of the term,
something that appears to us as it actually is. For the secondary sense, we will use terms like
“semblance,” “mere appearance,” “specious appearance,” and the like. We now turn to the third
and fourth senses of “appearance”.
</p>
