<p id="PC_50c" class="noindent">
<b>5. <i>Etymology of “phenomenology.” Division of § 7.</i></b> The word “phenomenology” is based on two
Greek terms: phainomenon + logos just as “theology” is based on theos + logos and “biology” on
bios + logos. However, we are not using “phenomenology” in the superficial sense of the “science
of phenomena.” We will examine each of the two Greek words separately: phainomenon in
subsection “A” and logos in subsection “B.” Subsection “C” will then combine the two terms into
a preliminary definition of phenomenology.
<br />
&nbsp;&nbsp;The history of the word itself (which presumably first arose in the school of Christian
Wolff, 1679-1754) is of no importance here.
<button id="Btn50c1" style="color:magenta;">◊</button>
<dialog id="Dlg50c1">
    <p>
        In <a href="https://www.beyng.com/gaselis/?vol=17&amp;pg=5">GA 17: 5</a>, n. = 3, n. Heidegger says the term “phenomenology” was first
        used by Johann Heinrich Lambert (1728-77) in his 1764 two-volume work on logic, <i>Neues Organon</i> 
        (see Bibliography). The word itself first appears in that work at p. 4.22f. in the Vorrede
        to vol. 1 where it is simply called “die Lehre von dem Schein.” 
        The second half of vol. 2, pp. 215-435, is entitled 
        “Phänomenologie oder die Lehre von dem Schein” and discusses how to avoid
        illusion and adjudicate sensible, psychological, moral, and probable Scheine. 
        See Karl Schuhmann, “‘Phenomenology’: A reflection on the history of the term,” 
        in <i>The Routledge Companion to Phenomenology</i>, ed. Sebastian Luft and Søren
        Overgaard, London: Routledge, 2021, 657-88.
    </p>
    <p>
        [Roughly: Phenomenology is concerned in general with determining what is real
        and true in every kind of appearance. To that end it works out the specific causes
        and circumstances that produce and transform appearances, so that from
        appearances one can infer what is real and true.]
    </p>
    <form style="float:right;" method="dialog">
        <button>Close</button>
    </form>
</dialog>

</p>