<p id="PC_62b" class="noindent">
<b>36. <i>Two forms of “transcendental.”</i></b> (1) In the metaphysical tradition, being pertains universally
to each and every thing. However, it is not a genus of things; rather, the being of things <i>transcends</i>
all genera. Thus, in metaphysics it is the <i>transcendens</i> pure and simple.<span style="color:magenta;" title="
[But here] it definitely does not mean transcendens in the scholastic and Greek-Platonic sense of koinon 
[common-to-allthings], despite all the metaphysical resonance [of the word “transcendens”]. 
Rather, I mean “transcendence” in the sense of [ex-sistence as] ex·static—ex-sistential 
temporality—the temporal character of being, but as a “field”! The clearing [Seyn] transcends things. 
But the transcendence [that pertains to ex-sistence] is due to the openness of the clearing [Seyn]: 
appropriation.
[transcendens freilich nicht—trotz alles metaphysischen Anklangs—scholastisch und griechischplatonisch
κοινόν, sondern Transzendenz als das Ekstatische—Zeitlichkeit—Temporalität; aber
‘Horizont’! Seyn hat Seyendes ,überdacht'. Transzendenz aber von Wahrheit des Seyns her: das
Ereignis. GA 2: 51 n. “a].
Editorial note: Heidegger here draws a sharp line between (1) the traditional Greek and
medieval notions of “being” and “is” as transcending genera and species and applying
analogically to everything and (2) his own radical meaning of “transcendence,” namely the
a priori structure of ex-sistence as the dynamic sphere of intelligibility (= the field or
clearing for the temporal character of the being of what we encounter), opened up in and
with the temporality of ex-sistence. See the detailed analysis in von Herrmann, I, 380-383.">☞</span>
<button id="Btn62b2" style="color:magenta;">◊</button>
<dialog id="Dlg62b2">
    <p style="text-indent:2em;">
        See <a href="https://www.beyng.com/gaselis/?vol=1&amp;pg=216">GA 1</a>: 216.1-217.27
and <a href="https://www.beyng.com/gaselis/?vol=33&amp;pg=11">GA 33: 11</a>-18 = 
8-14 on the medieval doctrine of the transcendentals and of <i>ens</i> as the primary
transcendental. On the analogy of being, see SZ § 20, ¶ 2 and the note thereto.
    </p>
    <form style="float:right;" method="dialog">
        <button>Close</button>
    </form>
</dialog>
<!--
<span style="color:magenta;" title="See GA 1: 216.1-217.27
and GA 33: 11-18 = 8-14 on the medieval doctrine of the transcendentals and of ens as the primary
transcendental. On the analogy of being, see SZ § 20, ¶ 2 and the note thereto.">◊</span>
-->
&nbsp;&nbsp; (2) But <i>Existenz</i> as the being of human beings is transcendental in a unique and special
sense. (It transcends not only all things but also the <i>being</i> of all things.) <i>Existenz</i> harbors within
itself the possibility and necessity of the most radical <i>individuation</i>.
<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp; Disclosing being as transcendental (whether that is the being of things or the being of
human beings) is transcendental knowledge (in our sense of the term, not Kant's).
Phenomenological disclosure of being is <i>veritas transcendentalis</i>.
</p>