<p id="PC_70b" class="noindent">
<b>12. <i>Categories vs. ex-sistentials</i></b> We will explain what and how we are by laying out the
<i>basic structures of our exsistence</i>,
which I call “ex-sistentials” as distinguished from categories in the strict sense. The term “category” applies
only to <i>non-human</i> things.
<br/>
<b><i>Categories</i></b> Greek ontology chose things as its subject matter and interpreted them using the faculties of νοεῖν
[intellectual intuition] and λόγος [discursive thinking]. But when it came to the being of things, a special kind of λόγος
/ λέγειν was required.
<br/>
What and how a thing <i>is</i>—that is, the <i>being</i> of that thing—is always already intelligible both (1) in <i>itself</i> and
(2) in how it operates in any given thing. Because we are structured as λόγος, we are a priori a discursive understanding
of the being of things, i.e., what and how things <i>are</i>. The Greek word for that a priori understanding is κατηγορεῖσθαι,
literally “to publicly accuse someone of something.”
<span title="The verb κατηγορεῖσθαι (aorist infinitive) is made up of ἀγορεύω (to speak
in the ἀγορά, the assembly, or the courts) + κατά (against); hence it means to publicly accuse someone of
something. From that comes the “accusative” case, in Latin casus accusativus, which translates the Greek
αἰτιατική πτώσις: the grammatical case (πτώσις, from πίπτω, to fall, Latin, cadere, hence casus) that deals with
what an action (represented by a transitive verb) “causes” or brings about. Cf. αἰτία, which in this instance means
a charge or accusation.">◊</span>
In philosophy, κατηγορεῖσθαι means (metaphorically) to
“accuse” a given thing of “being-thus-and-so.” That is, in uttering a declarative sentence, we correctly or incorrectly
assert what we think the being—the what-and-how—of something <i>is</i>. The kind of being we declare a thing to have is
called a κατηγορία. Such a “category” is the alleged whatness and/or howness of a thing insofar as we address that
thing in an act of λόγος. In this book we will use the term “category” with regard to the structure of <i>non-human</i> things;
specifically it will express the whatness and howness of such things.
<br/>
<b><i>Ex-sistentials.</i></b> Ex-sistentials, on the other hand, pertain only to the being-structure of human being, i.e., exsistence.
Ex-sistentials express who-ness, the being of a person. The relation between categories and ex-sistentials
cannot be adequately clarified until SZ I.3.
</p>