<p id="PC_88b" class="noindent">
<b>4. <i>“Objective knowledge” is a privative@privative mode of our engagement with meaning.</i></b> The evidence shows that
knowing objects is based on, and presupposes, our prior engagement with meaning, which constitutes our very existence. 
We do not just stare at objectively present things. Rather, we are <i>fascinated</i> by them, and “just looking at”
stuff is a <i>privative</i> @ privative mode of our caring about things.
<br/>
If we bracket out practicial activity (dealing with things, doing a job, etc.), we’re left with our “mere presence”
to things. We can encounter them merely in terms of “how they look” (εἶδος), and this detached observing of things
can turn into an explicit way of regarding the world.
<span style="color:magenta;" title="Merely abstaining from
[the attitude of praxis] does not of itself turn into objective observation. Rather, such objective observation (1) has its
own source and (2) has such abstaining as a necessary consequence. Detached observation [cf. νοεῖν] has an originality
of its own. Just looking at an εἶδος requires something different from that. [German: Durch Ab-sehen-von wird nicht
schon das Hinsehen — dieses hat eigenen Urspring und hat zur notwendigen Folge jenes Absehen; Betrachten hat
seine eigen Ursprünglichkeit. Der Blick auf εἶδος verlangt anderes.]
[Ed. Heidegger seems to be distinguishing Hinsehen (detached subject-object observation as a modern scientific
ideal) from Betrachtung (in Greek, νοεῖν: directly “minding” the essential meaning of something). Unlike
Betrachtung/νοεῖν, which has its own “originality,” Hinsehen of an εἶδος has its quite different origins in the scientific
revolution.]">☞</span>
 We adopt an “objective viewpoint,” take up an independent
stance “next to” them, and reduce our engagement to “perceiving” them. We may then talk about them as they are “in
themselves,” then interpret and define them, and finally make propositional statements about them that we can store
up.
<br/>
This is one way of being engaged with meaning. However, it should not be interpreted as “going outside” to
gather “images” of things that we store up “inside” and then wonder how they might “agree” with things “outside.
</p>